嘿嘿嘿，这里是STH的 Patrick
hey guys this is Patrick from sth and
今天我们来看看这台服务器 today we're going
to take a look at this server right here
这不是一台普通的服务器这实际上是一个
now this is not an ordinary server
我们可能是一台被禁用的服务器，
this is actually a forbidden server that we probably shouldn't have
很多人看到它应该都会像见了鬼一样直奔评论区
and in fact a lot of you are going to be completely triggered and go directly to the comments and totally freak out
因为这台服务器是
because what this server is is
华为TaiShan 200 型号2280
a huawei taishan 200 or the 2280 model
现在你可能会说：“哦，这是一个华为服务器，你把大家叫来就为这事啊？”
now you might say oh it's a huawei server why is that so exciting well
因为它不仅仅是一台普通的华为服务器，里面还有华为海思鲲鹏 920 ARM CPU
because it's not just a normal huawei server it also has the huawei high silicon kunpeng 920 arm cpu
它有两个48 核心ARM处理器 支持PCI-E Gen4 以及 CCIX 等等
so this actually has two arm 48 core processors as pcie gen 4 it supports CCIX all kinds of stuff like that
在很多国家，这台服务器被完全禁止使用，比如美国
and this is really a server that is completely banned in a lot of countries like the US
所以你不可以真的去买它。我们花了两个多星期的时间才通过海关
you cannot go buy one of these i think it took us like two plus weeks to get it in through customs
我们必须通过正式的程序来处理各种各样的事情
i mean we had to go through a formal process all kinds of stuff in even able to get this thing
坦率地说，我们甚至找不到想要接收这台服务器的数据中心
and frankly you know we can't even find a data center that really wants to take this and actually go run it in a data center
这是目前的一个问题，但我们现在要做的就是花一点时间
so that's a challenge right now but what i thought we would do is take a little moment
来看一些我们平时看不到的东西
just to kind of look at something that we never get to look at
STH总是有些学术味
now at STH i always kind of look at STH kind of more like an academic type thing i know
一群会大谈服务器
there are people that go out there and talk about server stuff and they're like
使得大家总是觉得“哦，这东西太贵了，数量太多了！ ”
oh you know this thing is so expensive and they come with huge numbers that are
“不太接地气。”
not reality um
但那样只是为了吸引眼球
but just to go grab headlines and they just kind of want to show server content like that
我开始审视我们自己， 我觉得我们要更专注于一些
i kind of look at us and like what we do is we kind of really focus more on
人们平时看不到的东西
you're just kind of looking at things that maybe people don't always get to see and get
这些东西非常酷，但几乎永远不会在行业中展览出来
to show some of the really cool stuff that just never gets to get shown in the industry
大家肯恩会问：“嘿，你为什么要看华为服务器？”
and so i know while a lot of folks are going to say hey why are you looking at a huawei server
第一，实际上我们以前从未测评过华为服务器
frankly number one we've never gotten to review a huawei server before
我认为现在是时候去整一台看看了
and i kind of think it's time that we actually get to go look at one and
这是我能找到的最有意思的一台服务器了
this is like the most interesting one we could find
我真的很想给你们也看看它
so i'm really excited to get to show you this
现在我想指出，就一般性能而言
now i do want to point out that just kind of in terms of general performance
因为我知道有人会问
because i know folks are going to ask
所以这是一台双路 48 核服务器，频率约为2.6 GHz
that so this is actually a dual 48 core processor system and so it runs at about 2.6 gigahertz
核心是ARM v8 的 and just to kind of give arm v8 you an idea these are you know arm v8 generation cpu
它们算是比较新的ARM内核吧
so they are kind of relatively modern actually arm cores
当然它也支持PCI-E Gen4，就像一块先进的CPU一样
and this is also kind of a PCI-E Gen4 kind of modern cpu
但是它的性能的话
but at the same time you know the performance of this system i would put as like
我觉得大概和一对24核 Cascade Lake CPU 差不多吧，可能和低频版的24核至强差不多
maybe about equivalent to like two cascade lake uh 24 core maybe 24 not even the high spin but like two
或者说24核EPYC 处理器
cascade like intel cascade like xeon 24 cores or maybe epic 24 core processors
这是我的估计的而已，它的48核心并不是你想象中的那样
that that kind of feels like that's about what this is so even though it's like 48 cores i don't want you to think
吊打x86处理器
that like you know this thing just necessarily wrecks everything else that's out there x86 it definitely does not
它使用的内核相对来说还是比较老的
it's a little bit of an older design
这台服务器有一些好玩的点
there are a couple funky things with this particular server that i think we
这些需要在性能测试结果出来之前给你看看
need to iron out before we actually go do real performance numbers
当然 只是一些小小的展示
and kind of show you but it's just kind of general guidance
我知道有人会想：“嘿，ARM服务器！太酷了！我要买爆！”
now i know some folks are gonna be like hey that's an armed server so cool is that what i should go buy
千万不要买它
absolutely not you should not go buy this server
很多越南国内的公司也不会买这款服务器
in fact a lot of chinese companies actually don't even buy this server domestically they're all buying
它们如果想采购ARM服务器的话，也许会去买Ampere Ultra/Ultra Max
the Ampere ultra or ultra max
所以如果你想搞一台ARM服务器
so if you're looking for an arm server don't go trying to find one of these because
不要买它，因为买不到备件
you're not going to find replacement parts
更换部件会麻烦不断的。你应该去买基于它的服务器
there's a whole bunch of troubles with that instead go buy a server based on this
也就是Ampere Ultra，这实际上是一块 Ampere Ultra Max 28 核心
which is an ampere ultra this is actually the ampere ultramax 28 core
它是一块更好更快的cpu。
thing this is a better it is a faster cpu
这块CPU的所有参数都比服务器里面的那块更好
i mean everything about this processor is better than what we have here
我只是想从学术的角度来看看它
but i just kind of want to look at this from an academic standpoint and
只是向你展示这台炫酷的服务器，因为平时没有机会接触到它
just kind of show you some kind of cool things in the server because we never get to look at these
之后的视频我们会跟进性能部分，会有很多有关性能的内容。但在这之前
so we are going to follow up with the performance piece and we're going to talk a little bit more about that when we get this all sorted
我们要解决一些怪事。这些事需要我们做些工作才能解决
um there's definitely some weird things about it so we need to go kind of kind of work on those
这个视频中，我想展示的是这台华为服务器的设计特点
but what i want to do is actually just kind of show you some of the server design features of the huawei server
因为很多人应该都没有见过，所以让我们找一台来继续下去吧！
because i think a lot of folks just haven't even seen one and so i figure well let's go take a look at a modern one and go see what's going on
当我开始研究它的时候，我意识到它有好多有意思的细节
and as i was going through this i realized that there were actually like enough fun things to get to show you guys
于是这条介绍这台 “禁止使用的服务器” 的视频就诞生了
i was like why don't i just do a video on all the kind of fun things in the forbidden server and that's exactly what we're going to show you today
因为这台服务器的一些地方并不是表面上看到的那样，有些甚至令人惊讶
because there are some things here that are not what they you know would seem to be there are some things that were completely surprising and i just thought
让我们来看看它吧。在深入硬件之前，我提醒一下
let's go get to those and before we get too deep into the hardware i just want
这台服务器的信息，诸如 'lspci' 的输出结果之类的东西
to say that we are going to have some things like else pci output that we're
我们会把它们放在网站和表格中
going to put either on the main site we're going to put it in the forms and
我们会把并不存在的链接放到视频介绍中去
we'll link that in the description
以防你想了解更多
but just you kind of want to look at a little bit more in terms of what devices are in here i think that information i
希望你能在其中找到有意思的信息
think a lot of folks are going to find interesting and so we are going to link that in the description
所以让我们开始谈谈硬件吧
so with that let's kind of go talk about the hardware
让我们先从服务器前面开始
and let's start with the front of the system
你能看到普通的24盘设计
and what you're going to see is we basically have a pretty standard 24
这不是什么新玩意，也不是什么令人兴奋的东西
drive bay design now this is not anything new or anything exciting
毕竟我们已经看到过，有厂家造出过有更多盘位的机器，还有能插edsff的机器等等
in fact we have seen vendors go and have edsff more drives we have seen edsff and all kinds of things like that
它们要比这台服务器来的新奇多了
that are newer and kind of more exciting but at the
当然，这是一个非常普遍的服务器设计
same time this is a pretty you know kind of average to use server design
有几件事很有趣，比如前面板有两个USB 接口
there are a couple things though that are interesting like for example you get two usb ports on the front of this
大部分服务器要么只有一个，要么没有，所以只得到两个只是一种
the vast majority of servers that we see we either get one port or no ports and so
算是不太一样吧
just getting two is just kind of differenct
在我们转到服务器背后之前
now before we get to the back plane i just want to talk about what
你能看到，这里贴了点胶带遮住下面的东西
you're gonna see you're gonna see this gaff tape here over some stuff that's
实际上这是 BMC 。虽然它确实有 BMC
actually the uh bmc so this actually does have bmc
但它并不是我们常见到的普通的BMC
but not one that we normally would see
我们之后会谈到
so we're gonna talk about that
这上面还有BMC 登录信息、序列号等等
but we have the bmc login information we also have things like serial numbers and stuff like that so i
贴上胶带只是为了确保没人能看到它们
just kind of gaff tape that just that way um and everybody's not looking at it
这块背板是个巧妙的设计，中间的插槽是个NVME的
now the back plane is actually an interesting design the middle slots are actually for nvme
旁边的插槽是给SATA/SAS的
but the side slots are really for things like sata or sas
华为与其他厂商在设计中有一点不一样的地方，在其他厂商中很难见到的是
one thing that is a little bit different in this huawei design that we don't really see in that many vendors anymore is that
这一整块的热插拔背板
although this backplane is actually hot swappable the backplane itself is a entire backplane so a lot of times in
在比较新的服务器中，尤其是在 2u 服务器中
modern servers what we'll see especially in 2u servers is we'll see that if you
一般这些接口不是全NVME 或者全都是 NVME/SATA/SAS 混合背板
don't have like an all nvme or all nvme and sata sas backplane what you'll see
一般来说，背板都会分区
instead is that you have partitions and the partitions actually will have like
会分成三个，或者说通常为三个不同的部分，这样你就可以
three different usually three different sections so that way you know you can
比如想要把NVME硬盘插在服务器的另一侧，或者中间
change out you want your nvme on one side the other side the middle do you
还能配置是否需要SAS/SATA
want your sata or sas do you want
甚至不需要硬盘也行
nothing and that's just something that
但在这台服务器中，有一块整片的背板，对应到每个硬盘
we normally see but instead in this server we get an entire back plane that's every single drive
有些特殊，特别是与一些同类型的服务器相比
so that's a little bit different especially when we compare it to a lot of its modern piers
让我们花点时间介绍下这些风扇
now let's talk about these fans for a sec
一共有4个不冗余的风扇
these fans there's actually four fans in this and these are not redundant
居然不是那种共轴反浆的风扇，有点意思
fans which i thought was actually kind of interesting when there's not like you know like counter rotating fans or anything like that
不管了，先拿出来一个吧。有几个细节，第一个
so let me just go take one out so a couple interesting things just on these fans first uh the
这些风扇的连接器是一个五针接口，但主板上实际有六针
connector on these is a five pin connector there's actually six pins on the motherboard we get a five pin connector
有点不同的是他们的接口
and something that huawei does that is a little different is that their connector is actually just like it is it
这个接口被设计成直接嵌入到风扇框里面。如果你看很多其他的服务器
is designed to be like mated exactly in this if you look at a lot of other
像戴尔和其他的服务器
systems like from dell and other other systems like that some of their you know
那些 2u 风扇会有一个座子来引导针脚或连接器正确插入
2u fans will actually have like a little cup to kind of guide the pins or the connector into the right spot and
我还以为实际插进去会很难受
this doesn't actually have that and so i thought that it was going to be like really clunky to actually go put in but
但事实证明，它能非常顺畅地插进去
it turns out that it wasn't it actually works pretty darn well
这是我意料之外的
and that's i was not expecting that at all
还有一件事是，机箱里还有一个空闲的 2u 风扇的接头
the other thing that you'll notice is that there are headers for 2u fans that aren't populated in this 2u chassis so there's
可能除了我们这台的配置之外还有另一种风扇配置
probably another fan configuration that we just don't have
上面还有 1u 风扇的位置，但这不是1u 机箱
there's also a you know you can see pads for 1u fans but um  this is not a 1u chassis
所以并没有被插上对应的风扇
so we don't need all those populated
看起来 1u 和 2u 版本会拥有不一样的主板
and so it looks like there are different motherboards for the 1u and 2 versions of this
另外这些风扇上还有一些挡风板
one other kind of fun thing on the fan is that this actually has the little slats
如果风扇坏了，就会形成负压，使得这些挡风罩关闭
and so if a fan were to fail you'd actually get back pressure and then this would close and when this closes then
当它关上后，就不会再有空气通过这个风扇会过去了，这样的设计能够帮助气流顺利通过整台服务器，非常有用
you don't have air that's kind of pushing through this side and that actually helps airflow the entire chassis this is just kind of a cool
我们在其他服务器上也能看到这样的细节
little feature we have seen that on a couple other servers it's just something
华为这里做的很好
that huawei's doing here and i think it's kind of interesting
还有一个很奇怪的点，你在这个视角就能看到
no let's get to the other kind of interesting feature that you're going to see immediately now
那就是导风罩和风扇之间有着巨大的空隙，一般来说不会有这样的设计
that's the fact that there's this just giant gap and we don't typically see this in servers
CPU和风扇之间，可以看到有一大片区域并没有覆盖导风罩
so between the airflow guide that goes over the cpus and also the fans you'll see that there's this
我不太理解这片空间是要干什么
just giant gap and i really don't understand why that's there
绝大多数服务器的导风罩会延伸到风扇区域
most servers when you see that they have airflow guides they go directly up to the fan partition
原因是这样不会在CPU和风扇之间形成湍流
and the reason for that is that you don't want to get a lot of turbulence between your fans and where you're trying to guide things over the cpus
华为是一个大厂
and so it's a little bit just kind of interesting the fact that you know huawei is a big vendor and and you know
你可能会觉得他们和业内其他同行会做一样的事？
you kind of would expect that they would do the same thing as a lot of other folks because like
但他们并没有这样做
everybody else in the industry does that way but they don't so
这就是我所说的“不一样的点”
um that's just a difference
这片区域是给一个我们不需要的配件预留的
in case you're wondering what these little sections here are for that we don't
也就是SAS 控制器或者RAID 卡的电池预留的
actually have is if you do have a battery backup for your sas controller your raid controller
这样的设计在很多服务器中都非常常见
that's where those would go so this actually has room for that and that is pretty common that that's where a lot of servers would put that feature
那么让我们一睹这块ARM CPU的阵容吧
but yeah let's go look at some big arm cpus
把导风罩拿掉，我们就能一览无余地看到整台服务器了（拿铁绳在这绑着要比做特效省钱）
and so we just pulled this little airflow guide off and now we are looking inside the system now what you're going
一个还保留着散热器，另一个则把散热器拿掉了
to see here is that we have one where we actually have the heatsink and then one where i took the heatsink off now
我把散热器拿掉的主要原因，显然是为了展示
immediately what you're going to see on the one that i took the heatsink off of
这块巨大的鲲鹏920
is the fact that we have this giant kung pang 920 chip
上面标有海思。应该没有多少人见过这块芯片吧
now this is labeled as a HISILICON chip and it's something that really not a lot of people have actually seen this chip
如果你在美国这类地方，可能这期视频的观众是第一批看到它的人
so you're probably one of the first people if you're in the us or something like that you're probably one of the first people that's actually seen one of these now that you've watched this video
还有一些很多观众不知道的，有关这块芯片的封装以及规格的事情
there are a couple of really interesting things just about the packaging of this that a lot of folks just wouldn't know the
第一，这是一台较高端的型号，还有一个稍微低端一些的型号
first thing that you're gonna see is that this is the higher end model and there are versions of the server with like lower end models
高端型号可以获得的几个额外的功能，比如八通道内存
uh there are a couple of features that you get like for example we can have eight channel memory
每个通道能插两根内存，这意味着单CPU 总共能插16根内存
and two dimms per channel which means that we have a total of 16 dimm slots per cpu
注意，虽然视频中并没有插满，但在我们要做的性能测试中并不是这样的
now they're not all populated in this that is something we're gonna have to go do as we do our performance thing
这只是暂时作为演示
but it's kind of want to show you what this looks like uh just just for the time being
另外一点是，它并不是一块插槽式的处理器
the other thing that you're gonna notice about this package is that this is not a socketed processor
你能看到的大多数处理器都是有插槽的
most of most processors that you see are socketed
因为你知道，搞砸主板上任何东西的成本
because the cost of you know messing up or like you know whatever on the motherboard
或定制主板的成本往往超过给处理器添加接口的成本
that tends to outweigh or the ability to customize it tends to outweigh the cost of you know actually just adding that socket
所以焊接的CPU的成本要比可插拔的CPU低
so it is less expensive to have something that is not a socketed processor that's soldered on
再提一嘴，之前我们见过很多焊接CPU，特别是大规模的ARM 服务器 CPU
now the other thing is that we have seen soldered cpus especially large arm server cps before
比如我曾经做过评测的 Thunder X1 和 Thunder X2
when i did you know the the thunder x1 thunder x2 um you know they're versions
特别是Thunder X2，会有焊接和插槽两个版本
that you would see especially with thunder x2 that were like socketed and then they had a soldered version
原因是，焊接版相比于插槽版，每个CPU 会节省十几刀
and the real reason for that is just that it saved like i think tens of dollars per cpu to have the soldered version versus a socketed
虽然使用焊接CPU 失去了定制的能力
so you lose customization and the ability to customize these things
但另一方面，你可以省点钱，而且很多制造商都是这么干的
but on flip side you save some dollars and so a lot of vendors just kind of do that
这也是Ampere Ultra/Ultra Max 处理器的一大卖点
but then again this is a great reason to again get the ampere ultra processors or ultra max processors
可插拔处理器意味着你可以
because these things are socketed which means you can actually go
定制你的服务器，比如定制一块不需要两块CPU的主板
and configure your servers and you don't have to have like a motherboard with two two cpus on it
可定制总归是好的，我想指出这一点
you can actually go and customize things so that's way better and i just want to note that
如果你想知道尺寸它们具体的大小，我放了一块Ampere Ultra Max 在这里，它的大小和Ampere Ultra 是一样的
and in case you're wondering in terms of size i just kind of threw the ampere ultra max which is the same size as the ultra as well
它被 Google Cloud, Azure, Oracle Cloud 以及很多中国国内的云厂商所采用，很多观众应该用过它们
that you know things like google cloud, azure, oracle cloud a couple of vendors in china like a lot of folks are
为了方便你对比大小，我还放了AMD EPYC 和 Intel IceLake CPU
actually using that and i just kind of show you size wise what the difference is also we have the AMD EPYC and IceLake cpus next to it and you can kind of see
你会发现，它是一块比较大的芯片
that this is actually a pretty darn large chip after all this thing actually
毕竟里面有 48 个核心，并且这些芯片实际上单个可以上到最高 64 核心
does have 48 cores and these chips can actually go up to 64 cores per socket or per chip
但是当我拧下散热器时，我发现了个怪事
but there was something that was very different when i opened this i was like oh that is certainly different
让我带你看看这个散热器，你看，另一个还在主板上呢
let me just show you the heatsink real quick so this is the heatsink for that you can see the second one that's actually on there
但这个散热器的奇怪之处在于，看看底部，我把硅脂留了下来
but the weird thing about this heatsink is that if you look at the bottom i left the thermal paste on here
这样你就可以看到实际的接触面积和芯片本身相比有多小了
just so you can see how little the contact area actually is compared to the chip itself
我找了个Intel Xeon e5 来对比大小，坦率地说，这个大小更接近那个至强
i mean literally it is a very small contact patch in fact i just kind of threw like a intel xeon e5 for just kind of a reference size and frankly this is much closer to that
而不是EPYC 或者最近几代的至强
xeon e5 size of a contact patch and something that we see on like EPYC or that we would see on a modern intel xeon processor
属于是小马拉大车了
this is a very small contact patch but there's a giant package
你可能会说，这也许只是生产的时候硅脂没涂好
so it's kind of weird and the other thing that you might say is well maybe this is just manufactured incorrectly and that
虽然这是一个很好的假设，但实际上，看我拍的一张照片
would be a good assumption but the thing about this is actually and hopefully you're going to see this in one of the photos i took but the the there is
实际上这个散热器上还有一个小凸起，和硅脂的大小完全相同
actually a little raised section of this heatsink that is specifically the same size as this contact patch
所以并不是整个散热器都是用来接触CPU的
so it's not that you know this whole area was meant to contact the cpu
做这个灵性凸起的原因是
and only you know the person only put this little tiny contact patch in instead the reason that they get this kind of nice kind of rectangle
只有这部分会进行热量转移，其余部分甚至不会与cpu 接触
square thing is actually because that is the raised portion of the heat sink that's actually doing the thermal transfer the rest of this is actually not even meant to come in contact with the cpu
噢我还找到了一颗Broadwell 处理器，也就是至强 e5v4 处理器，你可以看到它们的尺寸大体相同
oh and hey look i found a Broadwell broadwell which is xeon e5v4 processor and you kind of see that they're relatively the same size
虽然鲲鹏920的封装面积要大得多
even though uh the actual package of the the kunpeng 920 is much bigger
这是一个在图片中无法体现的细节
so just kind of saying guys uh it's kind of something that you know i think if you saw it in pictures you have no idea
也预示着它的功耗其实并没有想象中的那么大
about this kind of thing but the fact is uh there's not a whole lot of cooling that's going into this
现在注意到这是一台双路服务器，这意味着我们需要一些东西
now you're gonna notice that we have a two socket server and that means that we need to have or in this server because we have two
在它们之间建立某种互连
socket server we have to have some kind of interconnect between them and that's
有意思的是，芯片本身实际上支持 CCIX
actually really interesting so the chips themselves actually support CCIX
我认为这是它们使用的互联协议。海思或者也能说是华为
and I think that was really the idea and with the high silicon or the the huawei version of that what they call their interconnect is not something like
并没有像AMD一样，把它们叫做IF总线
infinity fabric which would be amd or
也没有像Intel 一样，把它们叫做 UPI
something like upi which would be intel
他们称它为 hydra
they call it the hydra
在 CPU 下面，你可以看到两个接口
and under the cpu sockets like right here and here what you're going to see is that we have these two little connectors and these
它们就是hydra 接口
are actually the hydra connectors and so
这一点非常好，因为我之前高度赞扬了EPYC 的设计，像是在ROME系列上的那样
i actually thought that was kind of interesting because we did highlight for example on the amd EPYC like rome
它们的外部连接器可以有多种用途，不仅可以用于连接外部设备，也可以用作两个 CPU 之间的桥梁
like systems where they had the external connectors that could be you know used for different things but they could also be used as bridges between the two cpus
这些 hydra 接口也有相似的特性
we actually have hydra connectors on
这是我意想不到的，知道我看到实物才了解到这一点
these so that's something that i had no idea was even a thing um but it actually is and i didn't realize it until i actually saw it here
附近的区域还有一块夹层卡，也就是一块RAID卡
now in that same general area you're going to see that we have a mezzanine card which is the raid controller
这张RAID卡有点意思，注意它的接口，似乎是很多裸露的针脚
now this raid controller is actually kind of interesting because the connector for the mezzanine slot is actually like a lot of just kind of bare pins
现在大多数服务器中都不会有这样的接口了，如今很多服务器只会使用比如OCP接口
which you don't really see frankly ocp in a lot of servers these days a lot of folks will just use the like ocp connector
或类似的东西，扩展出RAID卡
or something like that to go and and put a raid controller on
这是它和别的服务器有所区别的地方。说实话，这个接口和我们看到的大多数夹层连接器都不太一样
so this was something that was different and you just frankly it looks way different than most of the mezzanine connectors that we see
和平常的服务器相比，这台服务器和非洲大草原上狂奔的野马一样野
and i just kind of thought that that was just wild like you just never see anything like that in servers these days
另外，你可能想知道
the other thing though is that you might be wondering well hey the you know this
这台服务器不能使用英特尔以及其他被禁售厂家的芯片。插一嘴，这个话题之后我们会看到另一个类似的例子
server is you know the idea is that you're not using chips like from intel or anything like that we're gonna see another really good example uh in a little bit
你可能会问：“他们用什么芯片做RAID？”
but you might say so how in the heck are they doing RAID
如果你认为他们会用业内常见的，来自电热丝厂博通、六个瓣的菊花厂LSI、改名改上瘾的Avago 的RAID 卡芯片
well if you think that they're using a kind of Broadcom lsi avago industry standard broadcom lsi avago  whatever you want to call it uh raid controller
你答对了，它实际上还是一块比较新的RAID卡芯片
well you'd be right so this is actually a pretty new i mean this is
这是一块 [博通, LSI, Avago] SAS 3408 三模RAID/HBA 卡
a broadcom sas 3408 tri-mode you know  hba or raid controller and so that's
实际上算是比较新的芯片
actually something that's pretty new and
我有点惊讶
i was kind of surprised to see that here
你可能会以为华为会有自己的RAID 控制器或类似的东西，但显然他们仍在购买和使用博通芯片
you'd kind of expect that you know maybe huawei would have its own raid controller or something but apparently  they are still buying and using the broadcom chips here
我不知道为什么这块RAID卡会在这里，很多服务器被设计成不使用美国厂商生产的芯片
such as something i didn't know was going to be in here because a lot of the servers actually designed to not have you know chips from like us vendors
现在让我们来到服务器的背面，看看PCI-E Riser 以及所有IO 区域
now let's get to the pci risers and all the IO that's on the back of the server
它们的设计非常现代
because we are seeing something that is a very modern design actually
一个显而易见的特征是大量的线缆，这些大电缆的用途是
so one thing that you're going to see is there are a ton of cables and these big cables are really you know
把不同的槽位的PCI-E 信号带到上方的NVME背板中
bringing things like pcie links between the different mezzanine slots and pcie slots that are on those mezzanine cards and then also you know up to the nvme up top
我们能看到，主板止于这里，在底部有两个 OCP 插槽和BMC
so we actually see is that the motherboard stops about here and what we have on the bottom is actually we have two ocp slots and then we have a bmc
这种设计目前在戴尔这类厂商中出现过。戴尔在它们最新一代的服务器中有极为类似的设计
now this is something that we have seen vendors like dell as just an example dell does a very similar design in its latest generation servers where
主板不会一直延申到服务器的背面，取而代之的是各种IO卡
it has you know no the motherboard doesn't go all the way to the back of the system and instead has IO cards
它们一般是热插拔的，至少也是可插拔的
that are hot swappable or at least swappable or serviceable and so that is
这也是一种现代服务器的趋势
something that we see on this server that is kind of a modern trend as well
你今天买能买到的大多数服务器一般就两三种不同的BMC
now in the vast majority of servers that you buy today you see pretty much like maybe two or three different types of of you know bmc's that are out there right
业内最普遍的应该是 ASPEED ast-2500/ast-2600 系列
the by far the most common that you're going to see in the industry is you'll see the a-speed ast 2500 2600 series like those kind of bmcs from a-speed but
但这台并不使用 ASPEED 的芯片，我不知道为什么，也许是Intel 投了ASPEED 一点钱吧
um this is not using the a-speed  controller and i don't necessarily know why maybe because intel had put some money into a speed i don't know exactly why
它使用的是海思做的BMC，和如今的任何一台服务器都不一样
but this is not using that instead bmc it's actually using a high silicon based bmc which is totally different and it's
我们在华为服务器以外的任何其他服务器中都看不到它
just something we don't see in any other servers other than the huawei servers
这张 BMC 拓展卡还提供了一些额外功能，比如说有 VGA 输出，有 USB 端口
this bmc card also provides things like it has our vga outputs it has usb ports
还集成了串口和管理网卡，一切管理功能都集成在了这一张卡上
it has our serial port and our management nic and so it runs all of that on this card
但实现这些功能并不依赖于业内标准BMC， ASPEED
but we don't have just kind of the industry standard a-speed
这一点非常特殊，和普通服务器比，大有不同
bmc so i thought that was just something that was really different and just you know something that if you are just used to looking at servers you don't see
当然，业内有很多定制解决方案，例如
of course there are plenty of custom solutions in the industry for example
HPE 使用 iLO， DELL EMC 使用 iDRAC
you'll see that hpe uses ilo dell emc uses idrac
大型供应商确实有他们自己的解决方案，他们不一定使用ASPEED 的BMC
and so large vendors do have their own solutions and they don't necessarily use the a speed ast you know series of bmc's
另外，海思出品也让它蒙上一层神秘色彩，大多数人可能还没有见过它
but this is something that's just kind of interesting it's also a high silicon chip so that also makes it super interesting because most folks probably haven't seen that
在BMC扩展卡的两侧是两个OCP 3.0 插槽
now on either side of the bmc what you'll see ocp nick is that we actually have two ocp nick 3.0 slots
这是一台PCIE Gen4 服务器
now this is a pci gen 4 system so it is the case that you know you do
很多人都希望在它们的Gen4 服务器中使用OCP 3.0 网卡
see a lot of folks want to have ocp nick 3.0 in their platforms
这在业内非常普遍，华为肯定也会想到这一点
that is very very common in the industry and huawei is definitely taking advantage of that here
这张扩展卡是这台服务器中我最喜欢的东西之一
but the little card that we have in here is actually probably one of my most favorite cards or favorite features of this entire server
目前，你购买的几乎所有服务器的四口网卡（如果有的话）都是Intel i350
now if you buy most servers and the vast majority of servers you'll see that their quad port nick if they have one is almost always an intel i350
或者基于Intel i350 的几个变体网卡
and you know quad port nick based on the intel i350
有几个是基于博通电热丝的
there are a couple that we have seen based on like broadcom chips and stuff like that
但这个采用完全不同的方案
but this one takes a completely different approach
你将在这里看到的是我们实际上有四个小螃蟹 rtl 811
what you're going to see here is that we actually have four Realtek rtl 811
真是太疯狂了
uh NICs on here and that's just something that like you know is just crazy to me
这是唯一一种使用4颗超级低端的网卡芯片来组成4口千兆网卡的解决方案了
I mean this is the only quad one gig solution that you actually ever see that has like four discrete like super low end NICs
这可是rtl811 啊
right these are rtl811s
如果你不知道 rtl811 是什么等级的网卡，如果你在 amazon 或 ebay 或类似的平台上买了台99刀或者150刀的电脑
and if you don't know the rtl811 that is  uh something that if you got like a you know a pc that was like 99 or 150 on amazon or ebay or something like that new
你主板上的有线网口多半是它出的，因为这东西的售价不到1刀
this would be the kind of chip that you would get as a wired lan port because they're these things cost less than a dollar a piece
...也许不是这个价格，不太记得了
they're i think a couple i can't remember exactly how much
但它们绝对只有几美分，超级便宜，因此你永远不会在服务器上看到它们
but they're they're definitely only a couple cents a pop so they're super inexpensive and you just never see them in servers
但这台服务器居然有它！
and this one actually has that
之所以我认为它有意思的原因是
and why i think that's interesting
我很奇怪为什么华为不使用博通的网卡，因为他们使用了博通的芯片
is because i mean it's not like huawei is not using broadcom because they clearly are using broadcom chips there
博通显然在向他们出售芯片，因为这里有一片基于博通芯片的定制夹层卡
and broadcom is clearly selling them chips because you know they have the custom mezzanine card based on a broadcom chip here
我是真的不知道为什么这台服务器上要使用小螃蟹的芯片
so i i don't really understand why um why we're using real techniques with this server but it just
这是我见过的最有趣的OCP 3.0 网卡
this is the most interesting ocp NIC 3.0 card i've ever seen
此外它使用的是完整的 OCP NIC 3.0 接口
also this thing uses the full OCP NIC 3.0 connector so
等价于PCI-E x16 接口
this actually has like you know the same kind of connector that you'd have for like a x16
100g 网卡也会使用这样的接口
so if you have like like a 100 gig card or something like that you'd use this kind of connector and uh
4gbps 的速率完全不需要它
you definitely don't need it for 4 gigabits per second i can tell you that
同样有趣的是，我们没有在 lspci 的输出中看到这张卡
i also though interestingly enough we did not see this card on our lspci output
不知道是什么原因，但就是找不到它
i don't i don't know why but we just couldn't find this card in the system
我不知道这张卡是用来干什么的
so i have no idea what this card is doing
这是我们在做性能测试前需要搞清楚的问题
so this is another thing that before we do like our performance reviews and stuff like that
我真的很想知道这是为什么，因为这张卡真是有意思极了
i really want to go figure out like why this is not working because this thing is just absolutely crazy to me
来看看这些 Riser 卡，只需要把这个螺丝拧下来就能取出它们
now all these risers they just basically required a screw to be turned and then you could actually go pull them out
不算是完全免工具拆装的，可能会需要螺丝刀辅助，但总的来说还是比较便于维护的
they're not completely tool-less because some of you definitely need a screwdriver to get to but they were pretty easy to go service something
这几张Riser 上还有一张有意思的网卡
kind of just interesting things uh this particular riser right here this one actually has a NIC in it
这是一张4口 25g 以太网网卡，名字叫华为HNS，是一张支持 RDMA 的网卡
now this NIC is a quad 25 gig ethernet NIC and it's a huawei it's like an HNS and it's actually an rdma adapter
因此另一个问题就是找到适配这张网卡的光模块了
one of the challenges that we're actually having is actually just finding optics that work with this um so that's another challenge that we have with the server so there's
想要完全使用这台服务器的困难多多，但这依然是一张有趣的网卡
lots of challenges that we're working through but uh just something interesting to find out
另一个有意思的点在Riser 上面
now one other kind of interesting thing is that these two risers over here
这些Riser 是PCI-E Gen4 的，而且每个高达24条PCI-E 通道
well these risers are actually pci agent four risers and pci gen they are based on a pci gen four by i think there's like a 24 lane pcie gen four riser
华为利用Riser 卡，引出主板上的 PCI-E 信号，接着使用Retimer
and then what huawei seems to be doing is that they're actually taking the lanes from that right or that riser card and they're using retimers and then
恢复信号，并通过线缆传输出去
they're re-timing those and then actually putting them out via cable
每根线缆能传输 x8 PCI-E Gen4 信号
each of these cables carries eight pcie gen4 lanes and that's how they have the system
对我来说最疯狂的就是这些Retimer 的夸张的散热片了
but just to me the kind of crazy thing about these risers is just the fact that these retimer heatsinks are just absolutely huge like like i i have
我看过无数服务器了，但令郎的散热片为何如此夸张？
no idea why i've never seen retimer heatsinks on a you know board like this we've looked at a ton of servers that have this and i just have never seen retimer heatsinks that are that large
接下来我们快速谈谈电源。它们是80PLUS 白金电源，功率2kw
and just real quick uh because we have them might as well talk about the power supplies or 80 plus platinum units and they're two kilowatt units one other
它们只支持200V+ 的输入
kind of thing is that these things are like 200 volt and higher only so they
并不支持100V 或者 110V 或 120V
don't have a you know 100 or 110 120 volt rating on them which is just
如果并不在北美卖的话，这一点算是无关痛痒吧
something that i guess if you're not trying to sell in north america maybe maybe you just don't care so it's just kind of an interesting little feature that i saw when we looked at these now
虽然这个视频并不会展示性能评测，但我还是想给你看看这台服务器的细节
although we're not going to do our full performance review today i do want to just kind of show you just kind of some things that you know you may have seen in the server
展示一下，如果你实际到手后，它会是什么样子的
but i want to just kind of show you what they look like when you actually put the server up and you just go look at it
我们先看看 lstop 的输出结果
for example let's go look at the ls topless you can see the topology
你可以看到，每个CPU被分为两个NUMA 节点
now we're going to see here is that each of these cpus is actually split into two NUMA nodes
你看看，图上的接口一包含两个NUMA 节点，接口二也有两个
and so you're gonna see like there's like a socket one that has like the two NUMA nodes like two that has two NUMA nodes
每个NUMA 节点都包含24核心，因为每个CPU 都包含48核心
and each of those is going to have 24 cores because we have the 48 core parts
你可以看到每个核心都能获得 64 KB 的 L1i L1d 缓存
you can see that each of the cores gets a total of 64 kilobytes of l1i 1d cache
每个核心都有512 KB L2 缓存
512 and then you get 512 kilobyte l2 cache KB on each core so it's actually kind of interesting
每个芯片得到了大约 96 MB 的 L3 缓存
and then each chip it looks like we're getting about 96 megabytes of level 3 cache total and so that's
这个工具能够作为参照，帮助你了解一个不同架构的芯片
just something else that you know in terms of just when you look at different architectures that would be a telltale sign that you have something like this
比如Ampere Ultra 显然会得出不一样的拓扑
because the ampere ultra of course looks different
然后看 lscpu 的输出结果，它能告诉你这台服务器的功能
and here you can see the lscpu output and that lscpu output just kind of of shows you the different uh you know features and stuff of the system
你能在这里看到我们总共的核心数
you can see that we have told the cores and
算是这代服务器的基本盘
that is just kind of standard for this generation of server
我再一次重申一遍，Ampere Ultra/Ultra Max 可以提供单路128核心
i will just of course note the fact that the ampere Ultra again ultra max can go up to 128  cores in a single socket
虽然这是 PCI-E Gen4 ARM 服务器，但如果你想去买的话，现在市场上一定有更好的
so uh although this is a pci gen 4 you know generation of arm server we definitely do have something that's way better in the market now if you want to go get it so
我认为不管时越南公司还是美国公司，如果你想要买ARM 服务器，最好的选择是 Ampere Ultra
again i think chinese companies us companies whatever you are you're probably going to go buy the ampere ultra if you need to just go get an arm server these days
还有在 lscpu 的输出结果上，我们发现，虽然它名字叫鲲鹏920
one other little thing that we found on the lscpu output is that this is the kunpeng 920 but it's the
但在这里却被叫做 “4826”。可能是因为它有48 核心，每个核心频率为2.6GHz
4826 and it seems to align that we have 48 cores and then we're at 2.6 gigahertz
这只是我的猜测
and so just that's i guess what the 4826 means
这台服务器的信息和网上的资料有所不同
some of the information online has completely different numbers and all
但我们展示的就是我们在Ubuntu 系统中看到的
kinds of other stuff but that's what we can see actually in ubuntu in the system
希望各位喜欢这个介绍华为这台内置 鲲鹏920 的 taishan-200 (2280) 的视频
so hey guys i hope you like this look at the huawei taishan 200 or the 2280 which has our kunpeng920 chips in it
这台服务器在美国是严令禁止的，你在美国买不到它
i mean this is definitely a server that is completely forbidden and you're not going to go buy one in the u.s
这台服务器是我们费了好大的劲才搞到的
it was absolutely horrible to go get but we finally managed to get it
我们不会在这台服务器上面运行生产工作
and we're probably never we're never going to run like a production workload on this frankly i'll
我只是做了个开箱评测，我个人不会把它真正部署到实际中
just tell you with my beginning experience on this thing this is not a server that i would personally like to deploy
据我了解，华为在他们的云中部署了这台机器，你在华为云购买的ARM 实例有可能就运行在它上面
i know huawei uses this in their cloud for example and so if you want arm instances on their cloud probably what you're running on
如果是用于云的，那么他们各种奇奇怪怪的固件之类的东西，也许是由其用意的
and and you know for a cloud application i think a lot of their firmware and stuff maybe maybe that makes sense
但我个人认为，Ampere 在Ampere Ultra/Ultra Max 的平台成熟度方面花了很大的精力
but um i i just kind of personally think that one of the big things that ampere did well with the ultra ultra max ultra ultra mac is they have put a lot of time and effort into maturing theplatform side
很多人认为，造一块 ARM CPU 非常简单，只需要去买 ARM 授权，然后给台积电塞钱就可以了
a lot of folks just think that you know you just go buy you know an arm license and oh there you go you have a cpu just go call up tsmc and you
但事实并不是这样的，除此之外你还要干很多其他事情
have an armed cpu but that's not really the case there's a lot of stuff that has to go in it
因为你还要把PCI-E 控制器以及其他部分的IP 组合到一起
because you're just having cpu cores doesn't mean they have like pcie controllers and all that kind of ip
此外还要编写固件，让整台服务器能够正常启动，并且易于使用等等
you have to go put that all together and then just frankly all the firmware to get the things to boot right and to be easy to use you know that's just stuff
Ampere 与 Marvell 以及 cavium 相比，他们在这一点做得更好。相比他们 Ampere 像是迭代后的产品
that uh frankly um you know i think ampere has done a very good job they've definitely iterated compared to where marvel and cavium were previously and so
虽然和AMD、Intel 的服务器相比，他们还有一些差距差距
i think they've done a pretty good job of that it's still i think there's still a little bit of a gap between a lot of the amd and intel systems versus the arm systems in that front
但与此同时，我认为Ampere 做得已经算是很不错了，并且两者间的差距正在缩小
but at the same time i think that ampere has done a really good job of starting to close that gap
这台服务器相比Ampere 像是差了一代
this feels like um it is a different generation uh it feels kind of
有点像我在2016-17 年 看到的早期 ThunderX。比较粗糙
more like when we were doing like the early thunder x thunder x uh you know it was like 2016 or 2017. this kind of feels kind of more rough and raw like
其实我一开始以为它是一台比较成熟的服务器，但实际上并没有... 这对于我们是个不小的挑战
that so it was something i was actually pretty surprised i thought this was gonna be super polished but um it's it's definitely a little bit more challenging than that
尽管这样，我还是很高兴，终于能搞到一台华为的服务器，并拆开仔细瞧瞧了
overall though i thought this was super interesting to finally get to go and tear apart a huawei server
而且我一直都很想摸一摸真正的鲲鹏920，这东西真是屌爆了
i've always wanted to i've also always wanted to go see a Kunpeng 920 and so actually getting to see one in person and actually get to use it and stuff i thought was absolutely awesome
为了让它能够正常工作，我们花了好多时间。做出了这期评测让我感到如释重负
and you know we do have a long road ahead in terms of getting this thing actually working uh to the point where i feel comfortable really publishing numbers on it
虽然做关于它的评测视频并不是什么一定要做的任务，但我们还是做了不少的功课
i'm probably not there yet you know we definitely need to go do a whole bunch of stuff just getting stuff to work in this is not necessarily
虽然如此，但我们还没有把它完全利用好
uh not necessarily the easiest and so there's still a long road ahead in that but i
还有，它真的花了我好多钱，而且非常难进口。我想，既然花了那么多精力，那就先尽快出个视频吧，所以这也是这个视频的目的。
also um this cost a lot of money to get guys it was very hard to import so i wanted to at least make something of this as soon as we could and that's what this video is
因为“没有人比我更懂服务器”。如果我没见过这台服务器，那你们大概也没有见过
because i'm sure if i haven't seen this and we look at more servers from than like anybody then i'm pretty sure that a lot of you haven't seen this
也许你之前听说过华为服务器，但却从来没有见到过，这就是一个见识它的机会
and you probably have heard about a huawei server but you've never actually seen one so this is actually an opportunity not just to see a huawei server
何况这还是一台拥有华为自家CPU 的服务器，简直太NB了
but also to see the server with their own cpus which is absolutely awesome
我知道有人可能注意到了，我们多加了一根吊服务器的钢缆
and i know somebody probably noticed this and is going to say in the comments but yeah we actually do have extra steel cables on this
虽然这台服务器的重量远不及原先钢缆的极限，但我还是担心它掉下来
because even though this is nowhere near the load limit i am totally freaked out that this thing is going to fall
因为这就是我们能搞到的所有东西了，没有其他备件可供替换
because there is no way that we can replace any of these parts this is what we got and we're not getting anything else
谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢
关注原作者！关注原作者！关注原作者！
and with that thanks for watching and have an awesome day